Hello, I'm Sir Rick Slytheres.
This is Father Steven D.O.
Father Andrew, unfortunately, decided to give you up, let you down, run around and
desert you in order to go to the Archdiocese Convention.
So I thought to myself, self, I thought.
What could I possibly do to slake the insatiable thirst of our listeners for content?
And so, once again, as this happened a few times in the past, when Father Andrew has deserted his post,
I will be reading you some texts from the ancient world, two different ones, two very different genres,
two different civilizations they come from.
The first of these texts is what is referred to by Sc...
as the Memphite theology from Egypt.
So this is a text from the old kingdom.
Now, it's kind of interesting
because the copy, as it were, of the text that we have,
is not really like a copy of the text.
In around 710 BC, an order was given
was given by the then Pharaoh of Egypt to car
the text into stone, into a stone monument. And so the text as we have it, and as I'm going
to be reading it to you, comes from this stone. But based on the language, we know that
it's very much older than that. We know that it goes back to the old kingdom in Egypt.
So we're talking a thousand plus years before that. And that's acknowledged by the inscription
itself.
because we're told, the reason we know it's around 710 BC
is that we're told that the reason the Pharaoh gave this order
for the text to be copied and carved into stone
is that the existing copies of the text in his day
in 710 BC were badly worm eaten and ragged.
So these are ancient preserved decomposing texts
being preserved by the priests
And when it is learned,
by the Pharaoh that all the copies they have are kind of moldering. He says,
well, we need to preserve this permanently. Which is interesting in and of
itself because it means that not just that the Pharaoh would be concerned about
these texts and preserving them, but this text in particular, he didn't do
this with all the texts, of course. This text in particular, and the reason I'm
going to be reading it and commenting on it a little bit, is a text that is
written during a
a very formative, early formative period of Egyptian religion as such. Meaning we've talked
before I know on the show about how Egypt, like most pagan nations, starts out as separate
cities with separate gods and separate religious traditions as larger political units come
into being that encompass multiple cities, then quote unquote theology.
in the ancient world and what this text is an example of was the way in which the
priesthoods and the people and those traditions would then be integrated
together into one whole for the new socio-political unit. And this particular
text that's referred to as the Memphite theology, it's called that because
part of what occasions it is that Memphis has become the capital of Egypt is
at the point where upper and lower Egypt are first unified. So this is where we first have sort
of a full Egypt as we think of Egypt. So Egypt is made up of two parts, upper and lower Egypt.
It's kind of counterintuitive for us as modern Americans because it's modern Americans
and probably most modern people. We see North as up on the map.
Right? It's out there.
down. So people will assume that upper Egypt means northern Egypt and lower Egypt means southern Egypt
and it's exact opposite. Upper Egypt is in the south, lower Egypt is in the north and it's because
that's the direction in which the Nile river flows. So it's upstream in the Nile as south,
downstream as north. And so that's the basis for calling upper Egypt, upper Egypt and lower Egypt.
Glory to Egypt. Upper Egypt was seen...
by the Egyptians themselves as being the older part of the civilization,
and lower Egypt as the newer portion of the civilization.
But so now we've reached a point when this text is being written
where they've been united under one king, under one Pharaoh,
whose capital is in Memphis.
So this text is aimed at doing the work of integrating all of the diverse
Relate
traditions and deities who are being worshipped and spirits that are being worshipped and religious
practices of all of those areas into some kind of cohesive whole. And that's done not just by
handling the practicalities, although we'll see, it gets down to fair practicalities by the end
the end of the text, it's not just by dealing with those practicalities, but by
positing a store.
things happening among the gods, things happening in the heavens that are then
paralleled by this socio-political transformation that is happening on earth
within Egyptian society. So with all that sort of set as preamble we will get
into the text of the Memphi theology as we now know it. The living Horus who
and prospers the two lanes.
The two ladies who
Prosper's the two lands the golden Horace who prosperous the two lands the king of upward lower Egypt
Nefer Caray the son of Ray
Shabala
beloved of toss out of his wall
Who lives like Ray forever?
So that's the introduction
This is talking about the Pharaoh who has
occasioned this text, sponsors this text.
this first Pharaoh. The two lands are upper and lower Egypt. Those are also referred to as the two ladies.
These references to the living Horus and the golden Horus in this period is another thing that tracks this back to the old kingdom.
In the old kingdom, the Pharaoh was seen to be every Pharaoh, was seen to be sort of incarnation, right?
right, an embodiment of the God Horus who was
the firstborn son of Ray, the Sun God. But notice here in this already related to the two
lands Upper Lower Egypt coming together, we have this paralleling of Ta south of his wall,
Ta from Upper Egypt, the God Ta, which is spelled with a P, P-T-A-H, usually in English,
paralleled with Ray, the Sun God.
This writing was copied out anew by his majesty in the house of his father, Toss, south of his wall,
for his majesty found it to be a work of the ancestors which was worm-eaten.
So that it cannot be understood from beginning to end, his majesty copied it anew so that it might become better than it had been before,
in order that his name might endure in his monument last in the house of his father, Toss, south of the wall, throughout eternity,
as the work done by
the son of Ray Shabaka for his father, Ta-Tatanan, so that he might live forever.
And then there's a little section where there are some pieces missing. There are four lines where there's some
names missing. It's the conclusion of this introduction. So it's a lot about, you know, the joining
together of Upper Lord Egypt, etc.
But now when we get to the
Seventh line of text and it picks up again and we don't have the
La Cune, we don't have the missing pieces again.
And we have this scene.
Gebb, Lord of the gods, commanded that the nine gods gathered to him. He judged between Horace and Seth.
He ended their quarrel.
He made Seth King of Upper Egypt in the land of Upper Egypt.
Up to the place in which he was born, which is Sue,
and gab made
the horse king of lower Egypt in the land of lower Egypt up to the place in which his father
was drowned, which is division of the two lands. Thus, horse stood over one region and
seth stood over one region. They made peace over the two lands at A and that was the division
of the two lands. So what's being depicted here is this idea that horse who was seeded
is the primary God.
of lower Egypt is the primary god there. Seth is the primary god in upper Egypt in the south.
And the fact that the two were disunified, the fact that there were frequent wars that happened
between these two regions with Sina's reflecting a feud between Horus and Seth, between the two gods.
once the two are joined together into this new political reality, well...
clearly Horace and
Set must have made up right so they've now made peace and
Well, how could they have made peace? Well, Gab who's sort of the original guy must have called all the gods together
And sort of sorted this out held a peace summit
Gab by the way you probably haven't heard a lot about Gab
Even if you're fairly familiar like you may be wondering why that's Gab instead of Ray the Sun God
but of course his father.
Yeah.
is the actual sort of original most high God for Egypt. And as we've talked about
on the show, like all original most high gods, he very early already by the old
kingdom period in text we have has sort of drifted off. There aren't sort of
temples to him. The worship of him is not like a live thing. He's sort of this
positive most high God. Part of the missing text, it seems like they were
to give as self-begotten, meaning the other ones come from him, but we don't know much
about him.
So this is sort of a brief appearance here where he's sort of brokering this sort of peace
deal.
Now I'll get a little more.
Oh, also noticed by the way that there's a place where Seth was born.
So there's still a connect live connection, right?
Right, with the paganists that we've talked about this was...
Zeus and the Greeks where there are actually several traditional birthplaces.
They had the idea that these gods who they were worshiping came into being might at some
point die, right?
And came into being at a time and even a place associated with it unlike the most I
God.
Gibbs words to Seth, go to the place in which you were born.
the upper Egypt gives words to horror.
go to the place in which your father was drowned, Horus, lower Egypt.
Geb's words to Horus and Seth, I have separated you, lower and upper Egypt.
Then it seemed wrong to Geb that the portion of Horus was like the portion of Seth.
So Geb gave to Horus his inheritance for he is the son of his firstborn son.
So this is pointing to Ray, right, the Sun God.
Sun God. And let's think about Ray, the sun god having drowned. This is about the sun setting over the
see. There's a sort of constant cycle. But Ray, the reason Ray sort of became so prominent
is that he's the first born son of Gebb, this most high god, Horus is the first born
son of Gebb's first born son. And that's why. So it's saying it's answering the question,
well, wait a minute, that's how they got separated in the first place. Why was lower
Egypt. Why was Horace's portion bigger? Geographic.
stronger, more predominant. Oh, well, that's because firstborn son of the firstborn son.
Give, like, to us a little better.
Gibbs words to the nine gods. I have appointed Horace the firstborn.
Gibbs words to the nine gods. Himalone Horace the inheritance.
Gibbs words to the nine gods. To this air Horace my inheritance.
gives words to the nine gods, to the son of my son,
Horace.
the jackal of Upper Egypt.
Gives words to the nine gods.
The first born Horus, the opener of the ways,
gives words to the nine gods, the son who was born,
Horus on the birthday of the opener of the ways.
Then Horus stood over the land.
He is the uniter of this land, proclaimed in the great name,
Tatinan south of his wall, Lord of eternity.
The great name, whenever you see it in an Egyptian text, the
name it's referring to the name of the Pharaoh, which was the Horus name, especially
the Old Kingdom. So that's why Horus is connected with this idea of the great name.
Then sprouted the two great magicians upon his head. He is Horus, who arose as king of
Upper and Lower Egypt. He united the two lands in the gnome of the wall, the place in
in which the two lands were united.
The gnome there is NOM.
gnomes or geographic divisions of ancient Egypt, kind of like maybe counties in modern regions.
Read and Papyrus were placed on the double door of the House of Ta. That means Horus and Seth
pacified and united. They fraternized so as to cease quarreling. In whatever place they might be
being united in the House of Ta, the balance of the two lands in which Upper and Lower Egypt had been
Wade.
Okay, so I know this sounds a little weird. So what's happening here? Why is Ta this God being introduced? Well Ta is
a God involved with sorcery and magic. We heard about the magicians, right, and ancient knowledge who was primarily a God worshiped in the South.
There was a lot of enmity between Horus worshippers and Seth worshippers
And so when we have this combined unit which is being ruled over by someone from lower Egypt so someone
who is seen as the incarnate Horus, they thought trying to sell this kind of Horus and Seth marriage
might be hard to the southern religious hardliners. And so what they're doing here right here, beginning
in this paragraph I just read, they're starting to marginalize Seth even though historically he had
been the most prominent deity in the South in Upper Egypt.
Instead, they're choosing another very prominent god in that region and sort of elevating him and
arguing that ta and here what they really mean is the worship of ta
The rituals related to ta sort of unites
Elements of the worship of Horace, right because Horace had had this connection to magic
this had come from his head and also write the Southern traditions really
reset.
And so, Ta's here being put forward as this sort of unity God.
Right?
We got to replace this rivalry.
So first we say, well, they've given up their rivalry.
But now Ta's being put forward, and particularly the cult of Ta.
We got to think about the religious observances here.
The worship of Ta.
This is being put forward as sort of, well, we'll unify things into and around
religious observance.
of Ta.
This is the land.
The burial of Osiris in the house of Sokhar, Isis and Nefis without delay.
For Osiris had drowned in his water.
Isis and Nefis looked out, beheld him and attended to him.
Horus speaks to Isis and Nefis.
Hurry grasp him.
Isis and Nefis speak to Osiris.
We come, we take you.
They heeded in time and brought him to land.
He entered the hidden portals in the gl-
of the Lords of Eternity, though so Cyrus came into the Earth at the Royal Fortress to the North of the Land to which he had come.
And his son, Horus Arrows, as King of Upper Egypt, Arrows as King of Lower Egypt in the embrace of his father, O Cyrus,
and of the gods in front of him and behind him.
So I'll pause here that this is going to continue.
And so now we're taking a cat, now Osiris shows up.
So take this circuitous route and we're getting sort of a very very
quick story so far. There's an assumption here that the original readers were
familiar with the story of Osiris of his death and resurrection and so this is
going to be another piece of this puzzle. So Osiris was from the south, he was from
Upper Egypt, but as that story unfolds, that story involves Horus, who is
related to him and Ray got to remember the Egyptian
practice of royal close marriage. So Osiris' story sort of begins short version, begins
that the south ends in the north, comes to involve Horus. And so Osiris here is now being
used, and his story is being used to help further this unification narrative, but it's
going to continue.
was built the Royal Fortress at the command of Gab.
Gab speaks to Thoth.
Gems speaks to thoth, Gems speaks to ISIS.
ISIS causes Horus and Seth to come.
ISIS speaks to Horus and Seth.
ISIS speaks to Horus and Seth. Make peace.
ISIS speaks to Horus and Seth. Life will be pleasant for you.
ISIS speaks to Horus and Seth.
It is he who drives your tears.
So, we've worked in a whole bunch of other figures.
years. And so.
So we're getting this brief, very abbreviated, and it's punchy this way on purpose, because
again, the assumption is you're familiar with the story.
But the idea is, see, look, Osyris' story, which is this very important story religiously
and is involved with the worship of Patah.
This Osyris' story, notice how it involves all of these deities, even Gabb, who built
the Royal Palace for Osiris, but it involves all of these deities.
So this story, this central story unites everything.
So really, were we really all that disunited ever?
And particularly here, you notice at the end of the recounting,
this story unites Horus and Seth back together.
But so now we're going to set aside that story.
And now we're going in.
hard on ta. So we've posited out ta is going to be sort of our unity God unifying all the stuff
we liked about Horace and all the stuff we liked about Seth but bringing them together and at peace.
So now, well, hey, tell us more about this ta guy who you're saying is so great.
The gods who came into being in Ta, Ta on the Great Throne.
Ta Nun, the father who made Atun, Ta Nun, the mother who bore Atun, Ta the great is
heart and tongue of the nine gods, Ta who bore the gods, Ta, Ta Nafurtum, at the
nose of Ray every day. So Ta he's up there, he's up there with Ray, right? He's up
there's a god he's on this other tier. He's in
tear above because Horus's father, right? He's a tear above Horus and Seth. He's on this other tear.
Notice Ta in these two different hypostasis, these two different versions of Ta.
What is what is Atom's father and what is Atom's mother? Right? So you can see there's a certain
slipperiness to Taws even gender. Taws here being set up as
this summation, not just of Horus and Seth now,
but sort of all the gods.
The worship of all the gods of all of these diverse places
that are now part of Egypt,
really this is all taken up in the worship of Ta
and so this cult can sort of unify us all
if you're an Egyptian of the Old Kingdom.
There took shape in the heart,
there took shape on the tongue, the form of Atom,
for the very great one is Ta,
who gave life to all the gods.
And they're caught through this heart and through this tongue in which Horus had taken
shape as Ta, in which thought had taken shape as Ta.
So one of the things Ta was associated with as just a God in the South was craftsmanship,
the making of things, the creation of things, the invention of things.
And so the idea here is that he's not just a shaper.
of things, but even the gods, really, were all sort of shaped by him. So whatever
God you're going to talk about that you might want to worship somewhere else, okay sure,
but the only reason that God, even someone like Horace or Thoth who are higher
ranking at the time, they really have the form they have. You think about them the way
you do. They've been shaped by Ta, which means Ta is de facto greater is the idea.
Thus, heart and tongue rule over all the limbs in accordance with the teaching that it,
the heart or he, ta, is in everybody and it, the tongue or he, ta, is in every mouth
of all gods, all men, all cattle, all creeping things, whatever lives, thinking whatever it
wishes and commanding whatever it wishes.
So Ta was referred to by his worshippers.
as the heart and the tongue of the gods.
And so this is making the argument, well look,
the heart and the tongue rule over the body of anything.
A human is ruled by their heart and by their tongue.
And so, you know, even cattle, right?
Animals are ruled by their heart and by their tongue.
Everything that's alive is ruled by their heart and by their tongue.
Therefore, if he is the heart of the tongue of the gods, he...
must rule the gods. This is why it's called the Memphi theology. This is the ancient form of
theological argument. His any add is before him as teeth and lips. They are the semen and the
hands of autumn. For the any add of autumn came into being through his semen and his fingers,
but the any add is the teeth and lips in this mouth which pronounce the name of everything from which
shoe into Fout came forth.
and which gave birth to the Anyat.
Okay, so this is talking about the other gods, right?
Coming into being and the Old Kingdom creation myth
with Atom where he spoke the universe into being.
This is taking that story.
There's also, as you just heard,
Stephen involved, I won't go into much work detail on that.
Some other time we'll talk about that creation myth,
but this is making the argument that,
Well look, if he's the top...
of the gods, then when this creation
it happens and sure it's this other
god who's creating the world, but how
is he creating it? He's creating it by
speaking, speaking, you got teeth, you
got lips, you got a tongue, right? Which
means, Taws, really the one who's
behind this whole creating the world
thing too, and creating the other gods.
Sight hearing breathing, they report to
the heart and it makes.
every understanding come forth as to the tongue it repeats what the heart is devised. Thus all
the gods were born and as any ad was completed, for every word of the God came about through what the
heart devised and the tongue commanded. So this is continuing that argument. Heart function for
ancient Egyptians and in most of the ancient world, sort of the way brain does for us, right? So we
We would say like sight hearing breathing like
that our senses sort of report to our brain,
whereas they would understand
it's reporting to the heart, the heart would then consider.
And so it's saying, look,
whatever you want to call these other gods,
you can call them the eyes of the gods,
or the ears of the gods, or whatever,
all those report to the heart.
So if Ta is the heart of the gods,
well, then see he's once again really in charge, is it he?
Thus all the faculties were made
and all the
qualities determined, they that make all foods and all provisions through this word. Thus
justice is done to him who does what is loved, and punishment to him who does what is hated,
thus life is given to the peaceful death is given to the criminal, thus all labor, all
crafts are made, the action of the hands, the motion of the legs, the movements of all
the limbs according to this command, which is devised by the heart and comes forth on
the tongue and creates the performance of everything.
Again, this is saying it's your heart.
We would say mind, but for them heart, that considers what justice is, that controls
all the limbs of the body, that controls all the...
And all these things that are listed here are things that were associated with other Egyptian
gods, like justice or hands, right?
Doing certain things, right?
The right hand being associated with war and these kind of things.
and say all those things are governed by the heart and what it could say.
if Ta is the heart, then he is on top.
Thus, in his set of Ta, he who made all and created the gods, and he is Ta-tanin, who
gave birth to the gods, and from whom everything came forth, foods, provisions, divine offerings,
all good things.
Thus, as it is recognized and understood that he is the mightiest of the gods, thus Ta
was satisfied after he had made all things and all divine words.
He gave birth to the gods, he made the towns, he established the gnomes.
He placed the gods in their 60 shrines.
He settled their offerings.
He established their shrines.
He made their bodies according to their wishes.
Thus the gods entered into their bodies
of every wood, every stone, every clay,
everything that grows upon him,
in which they came to be.
Thus were gathered to him all the gods
and their cause, content united with the Lord of the two lands.
Right, so see, he's the top god.
Hit back.
He even made their idols. Now of course we know that's not true, right? And so they have to kind of back that up a little bit because he says well he made their bodies the bodies is referring to the idols. That's why it says of wood of stone of clay.
It talks about them entering into those bodies, right? As we talked about how idolatry worked in the ancient world.
But they say, well, all those things, the wood, the stove, the clay, they were all grown
on him, like he's kind of the earth itself, right?
So he kind of made those things.
And so, indirectly, yes, someone made that idle out of wood,
but he made the wood.
So there you go, right?
This is all by way of argument.
Now this is being performed as an argument
because at the time this text is coming out, right?
Memphis is the new capital,
meaning Memphis is now the Supreme City.
And the cult of time, Memphis is now
going to be the Supreme sort of Veronica cult.
And this is an argument.
put forward for why that is correct and right to these other cities that worship, you know,
upwards of 60 other gods and had long histories and stuff of doing so. And where other gods cults
had been more predominant over Ta until very recently. And so, but all of this is an argument.
It's an argument being made. It's not presenting things that were already believed. It's being imposed.
and
the socio-political reality of Egypt now having come together as one whole and
being ruled from Memphis is a big part of the evidence that this is true.
It's sort of a circular thing. Well how do we know that it is right that Memphis
now rules over all of Egypt and Taz being worshipped as the most powerful God?
Well we know that that is right because it happened and Taz the most powerful
Right, and here's the argument.
This is not a way of arguing that would work in the modern world, but with your village
atheist, but we have to get her back into the ancient pagan world.
And so then the text concludes, the great throne that gives joy to the heart of the gods
and the house of Ta is the granary of Ta Tenen, the mistress of all life, through which the
sustenance of the two lands is provided.
Owing to the fact that Osiris was drowned in his water, Isis and Neftus,
looked out, beheld him and attended to him. Horus quickly commanded Isis and Neffis to
grasp Osiris and prevent him drowning. They heated in time and brought him to land.
He entered the hidden portals in the glory of the Lords of Eternity and the steps of him
who rises in the horizon. On the ways of Ray at the Great Throne, he entered the palace
and joined the gods of Tatenin Patah Lord of years. So we get at other recap of the Osiris
story, the Osiris story of him drowning a
returning life is really about the cycle of the seasons, the flooding of the
Nile, that's why it's a drowning death. The flooding of the Nile that then
deposits silt, which allows for the growing of fertile crops, comes in its time.
Ta Tenen here is a goddess who is associated with the harvest, who are now told
is oh by the way also Ta, the the same person, essentially, this is a
the hypostasis of ta.
But also see ta is really in the background of this.
So Cyrus.
story, this is all being pulled together again. Thus Osiris came into the earth at the Royal
Fortress to the north of the land, to which he had come, as San Horus arose as King of
Upper Egypt, arose as King of Lower Egypt in the embrace of his father Osiris and of the
gods in front of him and behind him. So this sums it up, and so this is why we are now
being all governed from Memphis by the Income.
Hardenhorus, the current Pharaoh, and the way we are going to express that is through
participating in the Cult of Ta.
That's the sort of end result of that text.
So I wanted to read that text because it was sort of interesting in terms of giving an
idea of what theology looked like in the ancient world.
Part of the reason why that's important on this show is we've tried to talk a lot about
How?
So theology works in the Old Testament.
And there are a lot of places in the Old Testament that we've talked about where theology
is done in this sort of ancient way, where a familiar story, like the story of the flood,
is taken and retold, but retold with differences and with a purpose.
And so that was a way of doing theology.
was a way of saying who is truly God.
They didn't do theology the way Thomas Aquinas did theology in the Torah.
Then I'm not picking on Thomas Aquinas, they didn't do it the way St. Gregory, Paul and
Moss are St. Basil the Great did it either.
We're in a fundamentally different time and place.
They did theology by taking these familiar stories, these myth-hope-poahic stories, and
reframing them and reframing them with a specific intent to teach certain things.
things, a polemic intent often to say, well, no, these other folks haven't wrong, and
to recast and reshape theological thinking in a different kind of way.
And so that was an Egyptian example of that, of taking the Osiris myth, taking relationships
between the gods and things, and recasting them and retelling the story in this new way
with this sort of socio-political.
end, which wasn't separate at the time from our religious end. And so as I said, that's
something we see reflected in certain places when bail languages used in the Old Testament
or where ancient Near Eastern flood stories are referenced but changed and it's often
inverted in certain ways. So all that said, that's why I wanted to read that one. We're
sort of going to now have something completely different.
And we're going to read a very different kind of text from a long time later.
This is somewhere in the middle of the First Millennium BC.
This is a Babylonian text.
And I say it's completely different because this is not theological in the least.
It does not have any direct tie to anything we really talk about on the show.
It is literally just funny.
I don't mean it's fun.
like we look back and point at it and laugh. I mean it's funny like the genre of this Babylonian text is dark comedy.
Very dark comedy. So you've been worried about the very dark already.
What you find in Mesopotamian culture is particularly pessimistic.
About everything. When you start reading a lot of legachadian texts and stuff,
Sumerian stuff is even worse.
Very pessimistic.
You even think about like the epic of Gilgamesh.
Does not have a happy ending, even remotely,
for anybody involved.
They don't do happy endings.
Things that ended death comes when you don't want it.
The gods that they worship don't particularly like them.
Not like they don't like the gods.
The gods don't like humans.
Like not only do they not care,
there's some antipathy there.
a lot of that.
the Mesopotamian worship is aimed at sort of warding them off and keeping the
boy. So it's a very pessimistic culture. So when they decided to do comedy, when
they decided to be funny, it ends up being sort of super dark. So this is you've
been warned. This is this is a text a comedy that's set up as a dialogue between
a servant and his master. So the servant and the master are just are just
talking back and
fourth, so it's almost like a comedy skit. This is essentially an ancient Babylonian comedy skit.
Servant listen to me, yes master, yes, quickly get me the chariot and hitch it up for me so I can
drive to the palace. Drive master, drive, it will bring you where you want to go. The others will
be outclassed, the prince will pay attention to you. No servant, I will certainly not drive to the palace.
Do not drive, man.
Master, do not drive. The Prince will send you off on a mission. He will send you on a
journey that you do not know. He will expose you to discomfort day and night.
Servant listen to me. Yes, Master, yes. Quickly bring me water to wash my hands. Give it to
me so I can dine. Dine, Master, dine. Regular dining expands the inner self. He who eats
well is his own God. Shammosh goes with him whose hands are washed. No servant I will certainly
not dying. Do not
not dying master, do not dine, hunger than eating thirst than drinking.
This is what agrees with a man.
Servant listen to me.
Yes master, yes.
Quickly give me that chariot and hitch it up so I could drive in the open country.
Drive master, drive the roaming man has a full stomach.
So the roaming dog cracks open the bone.
The roaming bird will find a nesting place.
The wandering wild ram has all the grass he wants.
No, sir, then I will certainly not drive to the open country.
Do not drive, master.
Do not drive.
The roaming man loses his reason.
The roving dog breaks his teeth.
The roaming bird puts his home in the niche of a wall, and the wandering wild-ass has to
live in the open.
Sir, if it listened to me, yes, master, yes, I'm going to make a household and have a son.
Do it, master, do it.
The man who makes a household, no, I will certainly not make a household.
Who not make a household?
The one who follows such a course is broken up his father's household.
He has gone in a door called the master.
The man with a wife and child is credulous.
Two-thirds of fool.
Servant listen to me.
Yes, master, yes.
I will do something dishonest.
So do it, master, do it.
Unless you do something dishonest, what will you have to wear?
Who will give you anything so you can fill your stomach?
No, servant.
I will certainly not do something dishonest.
You not do it, man.
Master, do not do it. The man who does something dishonest is executed or skinned alive or blinded
or apprehended or jailed.
Servant listen to me, yes Master, yes, I'll fall in love with a woman. Go, fall in love,
Master, fall in love. The man who falls in love with a woman forgets sorrow and care. No
servant, I'll certainly not fall in love with a woman. Do not fall in love, Master, do
not fall in love. A woman is a pitfall, a pitfall, a hole, a ditch. A woman is a sharp iron
dagger that's
lashes a man's heart.
Servant listed to me, yes, Vastor, yes.
Quickly bring me water to wash my hands, give it to me so I can sacrifice to my God.
Sacrifice Vastor, sacrifice.
The man who sacrifices to his God makes a satisfying transaction.
He makes a loan upon loan.
No servant else certainly not sacrifice to my God.
Do not sacrifice Vastor, do not sacrifice.
You will train your God to follow you around like a dog.
require of you rights or a magic figurine or what have you
you. servant listen to me, yes master, yes, I will make loans. So make the master, make
them the man who makes loans, his grain is filled, his grain while his interest is profit.
no servant, I'll certainly not make loans. Do not make them master. Do not make them.
loaning is well, maybe you will need to add this. Do not make the master. Do not make them.
His sweetest falling in love.
love, getting back as painful as giving birth. They will consume your grain, be always
abusing you, and finally they will swindle you out of the interest on your grain."
Servant listen to me, yes, Master, yes, I'll do a good deed for my country. So do it, Master,
do it. The man who does a good deed for his country, his good deed rests in Marduk's
basket. No, servant, I'll certainly not do a good deed for my country. Do not do it, Master,
do not do it. Go up on the ancient ruin heaps and walk around.
Look at the skulls of the lowly and great, which was the doer of evil and which was the doer of good deeds.
Servant, listen to me, yes master, yes.
What that is good to break my neck and your neck and throw us in the river is good.
Who is so tall as to reach to heaven?
Who is so broad as to encompass the netherworld?
No servant, I will kill you first and let you go first.
Then my master will certainly not outlive me even three days.
Brum bum ching. So, uh, yeah, what was all that about? You probably picked up
during most of it that the joke was sort of this this servant was just a
complete yes, man, like whatever the master said he was gonna do. He'd just be
oh yeah, that's what you should do. And then he turned around and say the
exact opposite. Oh yeah, you should definitely do that, right? And at the end, I
know the ending was a little weird there. You made out of gotten the punch line. But
B.I.
The idea was having sort of got around in circles like this this whole life.
The master finally sits down and says, you know, what's the point of all this?
Like, what things is good as another?
He's basically depressed.
And he decides, hey, you know what I should really do, servant is I should just end myself
and you while I'm at it.
you know toss our bodies in the river and then finally the servant is like
Maybe, maybe, maybe not.
That's sort of the bit. I warned you it was pessimistic. I warned you it was start comedy.
But yeah, someone took the time to write that story
at great expense and requiring great knowledge in a clay tablet so we could have it to this day.
And while I said, you know, it's mainly just comedy purposes.
what makes it interesting is that there are some real things reflected there.
right? I think there are people who reach a certain point in their life where
they're surrounded by yes, men. And some of us seek this, right? Anybody who's
critical of us, we cut out of our life because they're a hater. We just want
people who are going to support us and tell us how great we are and encourage us
all the time. And you get someone like this servant. But that kind of also at
same time disassociates you from reality.
Because some of the conclusions, like we see them aster in this story,
a covetous conclusion like, well, getting married and starting a family,
not getting married and starting a family, the what difference does it make?
Being honest or dishonest, doing good or doing evil.
None of these things seem to make a difference.
Why? Well, because the people around are just supporting whatever he does on other side.
.
And he eventually enters this nihilistic phase of just nothing, nothing makes any difference.
But in order to have things make a difference, there has to be good and bad, right and wrong,
better and worse.
And that means someone might have to point out that what you think is right might be wrong
in some situations.
And so that sort of path of constant affirmation does lead to a kind of nihilism.
And I think beyond the dark comedy, I think that text sort of exposes that around.
So maybe we learn something today after all.
So that's the end of Ancient Storytime with Father Stephen.
I hope this will tide all of you over until our next video.
regularly scheduled episode of Lord of Spirits, and give you another wild and wacky window into the ancient human world.